greetings greetings you want to talk
about the individual you want to talk
about god I want to talk about the
individual and I want to talk about this
notion of an A in ele Bill of Rights and
where that where that idea emerges from
like what is it what does it mean and
also kind of accept some of the
phenomenology of it of like how do we
experience individuality if we do right
is it a perception that we have is it as
am prehension that we have right um it's
because it because I think that there's
a sense I mean I like like hearing here
in Jordan Peterson taco talked about
this I think he talks about it really
well or at least talks about it clearly
um about this notion of of that there's
something like this spark of the Divine
in the individual and that it has
something to do with a couple of things
I guess I'm gonna do with the idea that
there's something so we're like of such
worthy of such respect about the
individual that like we can virtually we
have to we actually have to do like I
don't even know if we can like legally
if we can get rid of our inherit like
our inalienable rights right that
there's something that like the
individual can't even touch about the
individual yeah hence inalienable yes
you can attempt to give away right the
authority of yourself yes but you were
the one who is giving it away yes
totally right you kick it's it's in it
is in alienable it cannot be taken from
you it yeah you were the only one who
can choose for you right you can choose
to give that away but it's a do your
choice and so
yeah and like in in this this like what
with what I'm interested in
like with circling is making its in the
reason why I'm interested in this is
because it's it's making more sense to
me about why well I've always wondered
what the hell is going on when people
have this experience of being with
somebody and they have the experience of
being seen or seen in this way it is
almost like a religious experience like
it's almost like where people have an
experience of where something like a
human being is revealed in such a way
that there's something about them that
is so unique then it kind of glows and
people go into almost like a trance of
some kind right and are enriched and
they keep wanting to have that
experience and touch in on it not I I've
been wondering about like you know it
because it feels something like a
religious experience it definitely is
something that people kind of act
ritualistically about and want a lot of
and feel enriched from and I'm just
wondering if if that is if that is the
experience of something like seeing
something like the spark of the Divine
in somebody and I've always thought
about that that there is there does seem
to be something that like you like is
this way in which I can't there's no
there's a way which if I'm really
relating to you you'll always not live
my conception of you right like you lot
I'll never be able to like predict you
all the way or map you in some final way
which makes me think about you know why
[Music]
there's why we have a name right versus
of course of course if I don't count in
this because I'm my name is guy yes you
are a generic I have a category right
otherwise known as dude and I am mark
yes right great I am someone to be taken
advantage of though what like and I
think that even that we have names even
points to something like that right
versus a description there's something
that's like you want a function that you
aren't a means to an end in the in some
fundamental way so I'm like I wanted to
talk about that in a legal rights that
notion of its connection with the
universal or something that like that
there's something that is can't be
completely mapped or conceptualized and
in how that's experienced and why that
matters and where that comes from and
then everything else yeehaw mm-hm do you
want to go first or should I I think
respond I think I just okay so I don't
know if you remember I'm fond of saying
that reality is the ultimate other
reality is deeper than our conception of
it you know as I'm fond of saying
reality is infinitely deep in all
dimensions and in all directions like no
matter where you go in reality it keeps
showing up though exactly the way that
it shows up yeah right and in that sense
reality can't be any more the way that
it is than it already is
yeah right and it's infinitely deep and
it is the way that it is it can't be any
more in that way reality is the one
perfect thing this infinity that we get
to experience and you know like I say
what is this right ah it's a pen yes but
it's also blue it's also a cylinder it's
also plastic etc it weighs less than a
pound it's like each one of these
dimensions is true
mmm-hmm right but that's not all of the
dimensions there's an infinite number of
dimensions I can never know this thing
fully yeah it will always outlive me and
that's true of a pen it's true of an
electron but it's especially true of
deep things like people the deeper the
thing the more profound my recognition
of it is to me yeah so when when you say
that like you recognize the divine in
someone else what do you mean the divine
you mean something that is so deep and
beautiful and recognizable and conscious
like you're actually with a human being
you're recognizing another conscious
being that has all of its own stories
well it has it has all of its own
stories about what life is and what the
pen is and what it what it is and what
matters and what's beautiful all right
right and so you've got this other okay
so I'm gonna say two more things that's
it to set a context and then I'm gonna
give it back to you mm-hmm so there's
you can say first position which is
where you see from your own perspective
and this is a baby
they only basically see their own
perspective they don't recognize that
there are other perspectives right
remember you you take the ball and it's
red on one side and blue on the other
side and you show them it's red it's red
it's blue and then you show them the red
side and you say what's what color are
you seeing and they say red and you say
now what color am I seeing
and they say rent because they don't
know how to understand another
perspective well they're locked in first
position right but then when they grow
they get to the point where they go oh
I'm seeing red therefore you're seeing
blue and if you turn the blue side
they'll say I'm seeing blue and you're
seeing red because now they can
understand perspective they can now do a
second position shift
mmm-hmm great right right and that
ability to see another person from their
perspective gives you a whole different
relation to yourself
right right the self that you are when
there's no other people is completely
different than the self that you are
when there is another person yeah this
is you know Sartre z' idea of the gaze
yeah but to be seen by another who
thinks and judges and who is conscious
like you yeah has you see yourself new
yeah right so when we see the divine in
another we see them and in seeing them
we see ourselves anew right now I'll go
a little bit further yeah we can say
that there's a third-person perspective
and the third-person perspective is
where you you observe the eye and the
you yeah and you can abstract out well
the you thinks this and the eye thinks
this and this other person thinks this
and the other person thinks this and you
can build a map of all of the identities
now that's deeper than just first and
second position is it that's you and
that's why scientists often feel such
enormous love for the beauty of science
and the beauty of mathematics and the
beauty of these things which is
absolutely profound because you're
actually understanding the universe as
other right totally and then you could
say that there's a fourth person hey
there's a fourth person perspective
which is that you can see lots of third
person perspectives and understand that
human beings even when they're being
objective bring all kinds of stories to
it you can say this is Heidegger yeah
that we're thrown into a perspective and
that even when we think we're being
objective we're coming from a place and
therefore we can start to examine the
place that we're coming from forth
position yeah right and we can can we
can continue up that with each level of
depth right Boober comes from this
fourth position right where he's yeah
his vow he's not just oh you're
different than me
right right it's and humans are
different than one another and the way
we see one another the stance we take
towards one another opens up a new realm
this realm of vow versus it versus you
yeah right
and this you it valve I'm gonna call
that fourth person perspective but it is
a deeper divinity than just me and you
yeah right so we've got that now I'm
gonna add one more thing Nathaniel
Branden talks about the he used to call
it the mutt Nick principle right because
he had a dog named mutt Nick okay right
and and he noticed that he would his dog
would play with him the dog would take
pleasure when they would pretend to
fight yes complex' right that there is
another consciousness over there and it
was because the other consciousness
recognizes that we are consciousness and
recognizes that we can play with one
another it's that and he changed it from
mutt Nick principle to psychological
visibility I'm visible in and I'm seen
by another right but not only am i
seeing you but you were seeing me see
right and that psychological visibility
as we add levels of complexity becomes
increasingly mind blowing towards depth
and that depth is divine and yes we're
hungry for that because whatever
consciousness is it likes depth the fact
that depth is possible the fact that
beauty and love are possible is divine
right and all of that is built on my
capacity to see these multiple
perspectives because if I can't imagine
you if I can't imagine what it's like to
be you then I won't feel that connection
you know feel the intimacy of you and I
together I won't feel the intimacy of us
as a relationship and what it is that
we're creating together from an
objective perspective from this
third-person perspective it's like wow
right we're creating something beautiful
right there's a we here it goes beyond
the I in the you write that then somehow
somehow calls the eye even more into yes
itself that's more it's more depth if I
can't see that then I'm not gonna be
it's not going to be as divine it's not
gonna be as profound right and it's when
you get at least to this fourth
perspective of the vow yeah yeah right
that that I can be with you in a certain
way in which we blossom together into
this consciousness where we go deeper
and deeper and my consciousness
facilitates your consciousness and your
consciousness facilitates my
consciousness and as long as we think I
know what you're thinking you know what
I'm thinking and you know that I know
that you know that I know that you what
you're thinking like as long as that's
going there it's like we just keep
expanding and when that brain s is that
that's ecstasy yeah that's static yes
okay got it
okay so so now all be quiet well cut a
couple of things like one of the things
I've been thinking about is in tell me
if I'm it is accurate so I've thought
about a lot of about this experience of
kind of first-person present right then
second person I jump over into you and
then third person which I could call
maybe we or it right
and then ad infinitum is I have a hard
time Ahmet whenever I imagine say like
seeing it from out of your eyes when I
imagine it I imagine it as if it's my
eyes and I'm looking at right and the
same thing when I do it like with third
person like third perceptual position
and when I do it to mine like I have a
hard time like finding a way to have a
perspective than isn't doesn't bring in
the inheritance of the something similar
to the first level of perception is that
is that accurate or is there a way that
I can actually perceive that isn't from
like a lived experience like when I go
for example if I take the perspective of
like the uber uber hits and I look down
I'm still kind of first-person position
as the uber X or first-person position
as you first-person position as me that
carry over one is that am I thinking
about that correctly am i imagining
because I'm imagining like yeah yeah so
so let me bring in a couple more pieces
just to distinguish two ways of thinking
about that okay not the only two ways of
thinking about it but two ways of
thinking about because I think I think
two ways yeah I think fundamentally yes
you were 100% correct you can never
escape that right there's the idea of
enlightenment this idea of non-duality
that somehow at some point you actually
escape that that there is just
consciousness that is not from a
perspective right now I'll say that in
Ken Wilbur's work right they came up
they came up with the idea of unique
self which is that let's say you go to a
fully non-dual experience right and the
mind is either silent or the mind is
happening
but it's just another bit of experience
like everything else and eater you could
say you're identified with the space in
which it's happening or there is no I
that is identified right and therefore
you are the space in which it's
happening but you're not this you're not
that you're not anything but you're
everything but there's no you that's
something there's just everything yeah
okay so even if you're in that
experience you're experiencing it
through a human body right which is a
time-space physical matter kind of thing
you're all and this is you could say
it's our thing toku right okay you're
seeing it in time you're seeing it a
certain scale yeah you're seeing certain
parts of the of the spectrum visual
auditory kinesthetic right so it's still
a limited elective and you can never
escape that well well you can never
escape them okay so that's one thing yes
you can never escape that well and I
think when you first started talking
what it brought up for me is that there
are levels of self mm-hmm like who do
you understand yourself to be are you
just me or are you me in relation to you
right or am i me and relationship to you
understood from a an a systemic
perspective or is there some greater we
that we create that we're exploring each
other and you are thou and the more I
understand you well the more what I
think I am transforms right like I think
I'm this until I really go on your ride
and the more I go on your ride the more
my eye transforms in that moment because
I use your consciousness to bridge me
into a new reality a little perspective
and that transcendence
well yes while it's still locked in
that's from my perspective and I still
put my stories on it I have you know
Wilbur again talks about peak
experiences p ee k vs PE a k oh well
right well you have a peak experience
where it's like you peek into experience
you have an altered state of
consciousness where you discover
something new and when you're actually
having the experience it transcends who
you thought you were and therefore all
of the structures through which you've
been understanding the world and that
moment of transcendence is actually the
creation of a new level of self and that
goes beyond yourself but you still bring
yourself to it and he says that when you
come down from a peak experience you
have to talk about it and articulate it
through whatever structures you have
totally so as you're having the
experience as soon as you start to name
it that naming process brings back in
the that level of self that you can't
escape yeah so on the one hand you can
never escape that self but on the other
hand it's that very vow experience that
creates an escape and that's not a full
escape but let's say an order of
magnitude escape and there's an infinite
number of orders of magnitude now that's
like like what is the thing what was on
Nietzsche what Nietzsche it was in there
was a word for what he called himself a
film philologist yes so he that's what
he got his degree and that's what he
taught he was a philologist he studied
languages and the cultures that gave
forth the language and how the language
embodies a culture totally and like and
it's kind of like that's the that's the
version one of now what's called Roman
etics right or it's connected to her
MuNet --ax like yes this idea of like
where like originally original of her
genetics is like alright can we
my understanding is like okay here's the
goal can i read the sacred text from the
way that it was meant to be read by the
author can I read it in the time
right right like like in other words can
I can I read it without my own brain and
like my understanding was like that was
that kind of like the idea or the goal
of it and that and that at a certain
point somebody went no you can't and
everyone was kind of like bummer
like but then then then who is it God
Mayer came along I think it was God bar
is the first person I had heard him talk
about it was like well no like that's
not bad news that's actually the way
history is made is like when we when we
go back and we read an old text we don't
diminish it because we can't read it
without a frame we bring our frame back
to it in a rich it and it's that for me
that a circle it's three making if you
bring it so to further your point oh god
I'm ER so I'm gonna contrast this guy
named Roland Bart French a guy right
with God more than the German I think
it's like God just you guys this thing
right so so Bart a really fun really fun
guy to read really interesting thinker
but one of the things he said is that
the text is just your opportunity to
riff right the value of the text is not
the test right right if you're looking
to find out what the text actually said
yeah you're on a goose chase yeah this
this is what you're saying that
hermeneutics is that is there there
there yeah there might be there there
but that's not really what people do
what people really do is that they
interpret the text and in the
interpretation that create its
interpretation is self-expression yeah
Internet iteration right and you own
that yeah then interpreting texts is art
and that's where you get to express
yourself and so the thing is how can you
in text interpret a text or fully
beautifully fun with fun and
entertainment okay now we could say
Ghana Murr
Wilbur says that there are an infinite
number of interpretations of Hamlet but
some are better than others right Hamlet
is not about a family vacation in
Yosemite right right this is Jordan
Peterson says look there's an infinite
number of ways that you can interpret
the world but there's only a few that
are actually useful that can actually
survive a natural selection process
yeah which involves other people yeah
which involves other people and so the
interpretation can be designed to be
just artistic where you put all of the
authority in the interpreter and you
just use the text as a it's like a grist
for the mill it's just oh I'm gonna use
these paints in order to paint my
picture yeah or you can actually learn
from the text yeah you're talking about
realities the ultimate other from
another person in fourth person's
perspective if you actually change
yourself yeah you can read a text in
order to change yourself rather than to
express yourself and this is where I
want to talk a little bit about like and
see if there's a connection here about
the difference between when I read a
text and when I read you what is that
difference like is there a difference
like like what is my involvement in
listening to you and understanding you
and in understanding of text so it kind
of gets this way tuck in question okay
good that is the question because we've
got this postmodern world dudes like
Jordan Peterson is is dancing this dance
of trying to create a post postmodern
world like so you've got post-modernism
but what do you create I don't know if
you've studied anything on meta
modernism met dad not explicitly okay so
there's this movement called meta
modernism mm-hmm right it's in art and
music and pop culture and things but
it's also in philosophy there's some
interesting thinkers in this space and
they're trying to do it integral has
done so I'm just gonna take an again use
this as a go text so you've got pre
rational right this first-person
perspective or the second person
perspective where it's like okay well I
want power read in the spiral dynamics
ooh right first person or second person
there's a there's a goodness I'm gonna
go into a mythological thing where you
and I are related and this is blue or
amber in the integral spiral all right
and then there's third person where we
can actually get objective about this
and that's orange or the rational level
right okay and then we can go fourth
person perspective where we recognize
that all the third person perspectives
are still caught they think they're
objective but they're really not and
this is green or postmodern and then
there's yellow or teal yellowing spiral
dynamics teal and integral which is the
integral level where you recognize all
of those perspectives and you find
what's right about all of them and
what's wrong about all of them and you
integrate them together right so that's
what integral is you could say designed
to do well there's another movement
another take on it called meta modernism
oh and that's this question okay so
because the text can be interpreted
however you want and it's just an
expression of self you could say in
green you know any interpretation is
just power
it's just self expression and so how do
you tell one is better than the other
well you can't it's all embedded in
power systems and this is Jordan
Peterson's critique right all there is
is power what we're we're as you say got
immersed going no no no there are better
interpretations mm-hmm right let's move
to this meta modern perspective where we
absolutely embrace the postmodern
insights yeah like we loved them right
right
Jared on Foucault and Bart and
but a Baudrillard right these these
thinkers who absolutely just tear apart
this idea of a fixed third perspective
right right let's embrace all of that
and then let's recognize that there's
still a deeper truth yeah we're not
going back down to orange we're not
going back down to this scientific
perspective but it is kind of scientific
but it's also post scientific and so
that frame when I'm looking at you the
post modernists say all I ever
experienced is a text all I ever
experienced is a text but you're saying
no no there's something beyond that
there's something there's something
different about reading a text and
interacting with a live human being I'm
wondering if there is so so I'm gonna
say yes there is and that looked and and
here's here's the distinction that'll
make if you close your eyes and turn off
the volume and all you have is your
memory of me then I'm just like a text
yeah there you go
the thing is that I can surprise you
that's it and there the individual yes
and to the degree that we're actually in
communication to the degree that we're
synced that our ideas and our frames are
in sync with one another I can surprise
you in ways that make sense tangential
it's not like where the fuck did that
come from what what I don't even
understand what you're saying you're not
making sense no it's oh my gosh you're
surprising me in a way that I can
actually understand it right that
transforms me and that can only happen
like with another human being who can
think the thoughts that you're thinking
yeah okay go on the ride of experience
that you're going on right and laughing
and I think that is different than a
text and that's the magic of intimacy
that
that's why we circle that's why we care
about soul2soul connection from my
perspective I mean that's the gold
because that's transcendent where you
and I become deeper together right and
now my self exists in a new way
because you see me and I see you seeing
me and I see you and you see me sink
right that well it creates a new world
together and it's ecstatic and it's
beautiful and when it gets lost yeah
that connection gets broken when we
break up yeah right totally totally and
that so a couple of things look I know
this is this is this has been my
experience with why I've always said
that listening like really listening to
another can be the most has been the
most transformative thing of in my life
it's also been like reading like reading
I think it's easier to talk about what
well yeah it's less it's like cuz
readings a little bit less dynamic
precisely because what you're saying but
there's also this way in which like when
you read a text that is just beyond your
comprehension
right it's just like right over there
right where you're constantly like in
order to understand what the author's
trying to do in order to think the
thought that the author wrote I have to
step so far outside of my own
presuppositions of understanding to then
try to understand what he just said to
think that thought that whether or not I
understand it or not isn't is um is not
the thing that like is necessarily the
transformative but it's what it took to
understand it right meaning meaning that
like for example with reading Heidegger
and Ponte and a lot of these guys which
are just coming from a completely
different a different set of
presuppositions I didn't remember read
over and over and over and over again
and I knew that they were saying
something that that I couldn't
comprehend but I knew but I knew I knew
to keep reading and I and I think that
what ended up happening for me was when
I started to understand them what what I
didn't notice until years later is it
actually not only did I understand what
did I start to understand what they were
sick with what they were saying but I
was able to start to see differently
right I was able actually start the in a
certain sense read the text of the world
newly and this happen a lot was was
circling like kind of reading Heidegger
and circling and reading Heidegger in
circle and I didn't really even know
what the connection was until I'm still
learning what the connection was but
this thing about like where I'm
interested in this this this idea that
you know is it you know now we're
starting to get into that that thing
about where you're talking about like
you can say something to me right that
that it actually furthers my sense
making right you can say something to me
about me and my experience that makes
more sense than what I could have said
right one is if you were saying those
things and I was in that moment thinking
another thought I would have missed it
right but when I brought myself back and
I said say that again and then I what am
I like you know what - you know what am
I giving you such that what I have to
think my own thought I stopped paying
attention to you when I give you my
awareness let's say or my attention is
it are you thinking are like am i giving
you over my thought stuff to think for
me like are you thinking are you
thinking my thought for me is that
what's happening you could say ideally
yes right that's really like I mean if
that's the case right if that's the case
I would have to say that's officially
really cool it's the most amazing thing
ever right it is the greatest gift that
you can give another human being yeah to
actually go on their ride to get them
think for you to let them experience for
you yes and to put all of your
intelligence and consciousness and focus
and for lack of a better term freewill
to focus your consciousness like Iran
says the free will is not about choosing
a versus B freewill is about focusing
your consciousness okay we're very
intent to understand with the event to
go on the ride when the intent to
transcend into the higher level
experience to understand that insight
that yeah yes and our own mind can do
that but when we when we give that kind
of attention to another human being
right I I say that love is the ultimate
trade that's love all right that's a
moment of love when you actually respect
someone and honor them so fully that you
go on their ride to really understand
their ride not to understand it well
enough so that you can then use it as a
tool to accomplish what you want yeah
it's not it's not bidding so it's such
that I may be actually someone different
by the end of your sentence yeah and and
that's why you know love is the ultimate
transformative force in that sense if
you understand love as focusing on the
other yeah
with reality being the ultimate other
yeah and the self the experience of self
and mind well being the ultimate source
of reality not that reality is not out
there but like your experience of it is
right your fundamental experience right
the other as part of reality as part of
the self experiencing
because you know we say what is
consciousness consciousness is God
consciousness is divine what is
consciousness consciousness is the eye
that's experiencing the self that's
understanding the self what is that self
yeah that the eye is experiencing that
the eye is like experiencing this thing
called life and self from this
particular perspective it are we open to
that yeah right meditation for me I mean
that's what meditation is it's to focus
on your own
unfolding blossoming experience in the
same way that you're talking about
focusing on another human being right
right totally so you can start to
actually I thought I've had that
experience too of like you know in in a
certain sense I've sometimes wondered
about like how is it that I actually
register a thought like do i register it
like I do the perception of the of the
picture do I see it like do I perceive a
thought almost like kind of analogous to
what I see in the outside world or is it
more alike do I perceive a thought like
the same way I perceive the immediacy of
the sensation in my foot great great now
okay perhaps it is an artificial
distinction right right based in the
biology that the wavelengths that we're
seeing through our eye is different than
the kinesthetic sensations of pressure
and movement and intensity and pain or
not pain right that we get from our foot
perhaps or a one way of looking at it is
that the information we're getting when
we see that over there is of the same
kind as the information that we're
getting from our foot it's just in a
different Channel totally totally and
yeah and in the same way perceiving our
thoughts oh right right
so when I got into NLP they talked about
five sensory systems visual auditory
kinesthetic or
three gustatory and they break down all
of our experience into these things an
auditory breaks into like things that
you're hearing outside and then the
internal dialogue of you're talking to
yourself right right and what they said
is that we we think that an experience
is just in one of those categories or
it's just in the auditory or it's just
internal dialogue but when we think a
thought and we're understanding it well
yes we're visualizing yes we're hearing
yes we're feeling and it has a taste and
a smell like the thoughts when we're
really on the ride of understanding a
thought it's a full human experience
that we can isolate out the internal
dialogue here are the words that I'm
thinking and I can write down those
words and that's why texts are useful
yeah right but the difference between
reading text and hearing someone say the
text area when you can hear all of the
richness of the voice tone and the speed
and experience itself as always there's
a deep profound thing including thinking
I think right this is what I got from
yes is what I got from NLP and that's
why understanding another person going
on their ride doesn't mean that you're
just understanding their words yeah when
you're reading a book and there's
they're talking a thought and it doesn't
quite make sense you don't have the
reference for it you're kind of on the
ride but you kind of not yeah they're go
they're traveling faster than you can
follow yeah yeah right now sometimes
when people do that in my experience I'm
gonna add to what you're saying
Oh sometimes when people do that I don't
think that they're coherent I really
don't think that they know what they're
talking about
yeah yeah right and in which case I'm
less intrigued to actually try to make
sense of what they're saying because I
realized that I'm gonna have to make
sense of it that they there's no real
there there they don't really understand
what they're saying right right but
sometimes I get - Wow no no they're onto
something they're describing something
which
profound deep coherent in some way and I
don't understand it I need to go back
over it I need to think the thoughts
until I can build all of the reference
experiences solid enough that I can
actually lay down in that experience and
feel it I need to be able to hear the
voice tone and differentiates the words
so I can understand what they're
stressing and what yeah I need to be
able to visualize how the ideas come
together I need to get the taste of it
yeah oh I need and and when it's when we
get the sense that someone's got
something coherent and deep that if we
understood it it would open up new
worlds that gives us the incentive to
actually work through it unfortunately
some authors in my experience they
really don't know what they're saying
and so when even when you try to follow
them and you really work at it it's like
there's yeah yeah ghetto like like I
loved Sartre I loved Sartre yeah
like he was he would drink I don't know
if you know this about him when he when
he would write his plays he would edit
he would write the play and he would go
back and he would edit when you write
the play and go back and edit but he had
a philosophy when he was doing when he
was writing philosophical work he didn't
edit hmm how come you know because he
was on a roll yeah and that role was a
unique role yeah hello challenges that
those roles are so there you syncretic
there's there's not enough markers that
you can follow him yeah and sometimes he
says things that like a really profound
and sometimes he says things that you're
like like I personally let me take it
out of the you to the I yeah I come
across it and I go I could spend an hour
trying to understand this and at best
I'm gonna get an approximation cuz he
didn't he didn't say it yeah yeah it's
just Gliss
the sizzle there's no steak yeah yeah
all right so if you're if you're up for
it I'll come back to this idea of God
slowly well oh yeah you go
what so there's so there's this part
about like Asha I really like the thing
that you talked about like listening to
your when you meditate you listen to
your experience as as like you give
yourself to another's ride in which you
love right as a devotion to them as a as
a testimony to your love for them but
also as like a respect and what you want
to get out of it that's a really great
way of putting that about that sense
because I often times when I'm
meditating I would say there's something
like you know most of the time you know
I don't I
and I think that I think that this is
fact I'm not sure but I I don't think
that we we actually I don't I don't I
don't see a thing that then I assigned a
phone to I see the phone like you know
what I'm saying it's like because it's
like my perception is already evidence
of itself it's already an evaluation
right the reason I'm looking anywhere is
because there's some ideal or a value or
a meaning that's calling it forward and
so things arise in terms of that but
when I meditate it's interesting it's
all say that i--dude i a shape letter
the world right wait wait wait a second
wait for the called or whatever's going
on to stop because you're breaking up
well let me know when you're back okay
great good umm I don't notice I don't in
order to read the text on the page I
need to transcend the shape of the
letter right like I don't read I don't
read the I don't read read it by
measuring the shape of the letter no i
transcend the shape of the letter and
it's only when I don't understand it
that then all of a sudden the shape of
the letter I actually have to look at
the shape of the letter
if there's something about when you
meditate that in a certain way it's
almost like you're trying to suspend
reading right in a certain sense for a
different kind of reading where you're
actually trying to like not get lost in
the content of thinking but then notice
the most like the quality of thinking or
the quality of sensing or the quality of
these things without having to read them
which i think is a different kind of
reading I think it I think I still think
it's a reading I don't think it's just
an observing when I've been getting from
it is it's interesting that you put it
this way because there as I sit there
and I just keep I keep witnessing my
experience I keep giving my attention
over to it I keep bringing myself back
there is this quality at a certain
moment where it does I don't know how to
put it something gets some a meaning
does come through that's something like
there's the source from which arising
happens at all like that arising happens
at all is it is it's a is it is a wonder
that can't be exhausted right like
that's now that's what I think is really
interesting like that I have to agree
with you sorry
it's like but on one level what we're
talking about the most ordinary thing in
the world the simple fact of our being
there right like the only thing that
you've ever experienced I've ever
experienced the only thing with
everything everything references or
presupposes the only thing has ever gone
on is our being there like it's the most
ordinary thing in the world and I can
explain I mean we can explain our being
there we can in fact we can explain it
down to the T we could probably even
like explain how it is that we perceive
it there in terms of neuro firings and
we will be able to like ad infinitum but
that there's any that there's our there
there at all can't be exhausted like
that
that's a wonder that can't be exhausted
like you can't get you can't explain
that away there's something untouchable
about that that I think that is
oftentimes is I think why is the gift
that keeps giving from medicine that
doesn't get old that's that's what when
I when you talked about reading when you
talked about meditating as in a certain
sense give it's really beautiful that's
a really great way of thinking about it
like I'm giving when I meditate I'm
giving myself over
I'm listening to my experience the way I
would listen to somebody I was in love
with their deeply loved there is a
communication that comes through that is
something like it says is I says I am
like it did like it says am and that
there is that there it but here's the
question okay and this is where I think
will we start to get into this okay I
don't think I don't think that that's an
experience that can get old and I think
that I'm wondering if how this brings in
how this connects into the individuality
existence and value like the locus is it
possible like the locus of our value is
in that it's like it's not that work
it's not that work that I am and then I
value that I am a value there there is
that looks like you're getting another
call because you're frozen what we're
gonna wait till you okay great someone
wants to talk to you I don't think
that's me Oh
yeah don't think that's me ah
interesting usually okay
yeah that's me so where did I leave you
off I have about 10 minutes by the way I
don't play oh yeah that's lucky you know
yeah so it only gets old mm-hmm and it
only stops blossoming from my
perspective mm-hmm when you insist that
it fits in your existing categories yeah
okay there we go right I I make the
distinction I call life versus carcass
Yeah right there's there's there's the
sense of transcendence where the we
actually allow the text we read the
world we read ourselves we read another
person with the intention to go on the
ride
yeah totally and we're looking for the
depth the profundity the beyond in the
ride that divine profundity right when
we're looking for that then it's endless
yes absolutely
but and most people like when they come
across it they put it into their
categories and then they fight for the
categories and then it gets old yeah
because now it now you're trying to put
it into a category yeah oh and that's
incredibly useful yeah as long as you
can play with lots of different
categories or the question becomes what
kind of category are you putting it in
existentialists yeah right in the face
of that they call that dread you know
that angst well write that here you are
and no matter what it is that you're
trying to understand it's always
infinitely deeper than what you're doing
totally that it's like yeah that thing
about that thing about like um where the
in its like light for example like light
in its absolute self revelatory disc
withdrawal
it's lightness right like it lights
everything up and in that sense it's
completely unconcealed but in it Sun
concealment it conceals right and and
that is either them at wonderment like
you can't like that's like I think I
think that starts to get at the
fundamental wonderment right it's either
wonderment or hell and what's the
difference that makes that difference
whether or not I open to it or whether I
close to it yeah right and you could say
the the the major challenge of the
existentialists and why they experience
dread is they look at the insanity of
our lives the tenuous chaotic nature of
human consciousness and the amount of
possibility that what we see is possible
in terms of love and joy and happiness
and kindness and intimacy and beauty and
then we see the the actual forms that
exist around us in all the lower levels
and we look at that and we say as you
and I always say it's like okay there's
reality infinitely deep in all
directions perfect in its completeness
it is exactly what it is it can't be any
more the way that it is and then we've
got our vision of how we think it should
be and when those two are out of sync we
make reality wrong totally we've got
that little tiny story which is so paper
thin compared to the depth of reality
but when reality shows itself when it
exposes our vision as inadequate yeah we
make reality wrong because it's
violating our vision and that's why you
would call it over standing that's what
I would call over standing right and
understanding is when you allow reality
to expand your perception and that is
wonderment that and and and also I'll
say one like that fundamentally well you
can you can approach experience open to
find its magnificent beauty and profound
depth right you can worship God you can
put your attention on God you think of
real care
rumi etc it's like they're like oh my
god how beautiful the effulgence of the
unknown moment is and going on that ride
when I abandoned myself to it is
absolutely ecstatic yeah or I can look
at what is and I can find everything
that shouldn't be the way that it is
yeah and that fundamental choice yeah
that unda mental choice right that's
where I think the game is I call that
the game of thriving it's using that
it's choosing to find beauty not to
constrain your beauty onto the world but
to allow the world to expand your
experience of beauty and they need to
enact that so that you build structures
that allow you to go deeper so that you
can build structures that allow you to
go deeper and to enjoy that ride so its
prosperity you're building its purpose
its depth and its beauty and wonderment
and ecstasy totally right and yeah
choice that's the fun like what is free
will free will is the choice to either
steer in that direction
or to make existence yeah because we
make it wrong you get a self that is
self righteous and good right I call
this the streetlamp life it's like you
are trying to make this self good and
you're in you're in the trial well I can
only make enough things wrong then I'll
be good enough right I'll be lovable
I'll I'll be worthy yeah and if only I
can build enough if I can only build
enough then I'm good enough right a lot
of this see let's do it allow the world
to show us new things and then we jump
on that we expand and then we go to the
next level and expand and go to the next
level and expand like a game often times
I think part of its showing involves
suffering right like it's part of the
inevitable thing about this and this is
what I'm beginning a lot about by the
way dude Jacob's Ladder
did you write did you watch that episode
a couple times yeah
yes yes I did that one that one's pretty
high up there like I I have to say that
one was he was he was hitting it on a
level that was intense
well the way that he extrapolated the
notion of young I've been thinking about
this like what like one of your main
ideas like this notion of the self being
a four-dimensional thing where then that
something like you know you know as you
as you talks about I'm reading Aeons
again his book Aeons which is really
kind of going in in it it's really he is
youngest there's a there's a coherence
there which is very attractive and it's
very difficult to follow totally it
what's circle yeah it's circle
circumambulating it like and that's the
thing I think I've always liked about
you is that you circle around something
you circle around something it's not
like you sound like you necessarily
knows Lucky's circling around exactly
but it kind of emerges it's it's worth
the ride but um but this kind of notion
that there's I I think I've been I've
been more impressed by this I've been
more impressed by this and in it and
especially since I look at people this
way through this frame it keeps being
true which is like we're always up to
something and like that's something we
don't exactly know exactly what that is
if you ask if I ask you what you're up
to
well it's a couple days here's the
question alright oh I've been playing it
with it like this if I ask myself what
I'm up to you I'll probably give you an
answer I'll probably give myself an
answer that is somewhat satisfying right
and it'll make sense to me and I'll be
able to explain it to you but I can
point to the same thing in this I can
say well what is it up to and you know
and I can look at the same places and I
can ask myself what what is it up to and
it's a different thing it's but into me
that is that kind of discloses something
else that's going on which is one of the
things that I've just been I'm fucking
really fascinated by that as an
individual there's this kind of notion
of like I am my own master I am master
of myself right I make choices and they
make decisions and I all these kinds of
things but like I'm oftentimes the last
person to tell you what the hell enough
to I can find out five years down the
road what I've been up to so this is
quality of I and there's also this
quality of it and I think that it is
starts to get at something like the
transcendent thing pulling us forward
that has this field guilty right
it speaks to us in our conscious it has
this it beckons our attention um but
there but but I like the thing that you
own talks about that there's this that
that where he draws the parallel between
you know like the religious idea of
Christ worshiping Christ and the notion
of my future are almost exactly the same
right that there is this kind of sense
that if I were realized in my full
potential like the ideal there's got to
be an idea like that that like hasn't
that makes it worth it right do anything
and what's interesting about it is like
when you look around and you just I
sometimes do this well just like look or
on our nose we'll watch people just
walking around and Cole what what are
you doing like we're all going somewhere
we're all like we have streets and like
with road signs and today we're all
going somewhere everything's going
somewhere and it seems to me that that
one of the things that I think that
happens when somebody's seen is it's
kind of like I've noticed that like it
seems like when somebody oftentimes when
somebody has the experience of being
deeply understood or deeply seen it's
when somehow in the conversation
what they're up to in a way that they
can't ever put words to what their whole
life has been about is somehow spoken or
defined or seen and that shines through
like why they do everything even why
they're sick and twisted the way that
they're sick and twisted is all oriented
in this direction that's uniquely them
in calling them forward that's another
big enough that's beautiful yeah what is
this self you know I I sometimes say
that the I yeah is telling the story of
the self yeah hmm you think using the
mind the eye uses the mind to tell the
story of the self and myself is part of
a world right right and yeah and there's
the self that we think that we are the
story that we tell ourselves if you
would ask me what it is I'm up to I'd
tell you a story and it would be a
reasonable story and it would satisfy
some of the criterias about what I'm up
to but what am I really I'm so much
deeper than that
like I there are so many more dimensions
to the self that I am yeah and the it
that I am that yeah beyond my current
story yeah and whenever I get new
insight into myself whether it's because
I'm circling and someone tells me and
now I get a deeper or an alternate or a
complementary or a further refinement of
my story
well I or whether I'm reading a book or
I'm having a conversation and I see you
I mean this is the other part of
circling it's like I see you and in
seeing you like I'm a participant in a
circle and I'm watching you get circled
and you go Paul and I go right I get a
new understanding of myself of the self
the it that goes beyond my story well
that I am right
right that's that transcendence and yeah
again I I think that's an infinitely
blossom never gets old kind of thing is
it going somewhere is there a future
self a Christ understand worshiping
Christ is there as something that it's
moving towards well my personal thoughts
on that right certainly but it's not a
thing yeah it's an approximation of all
kinds of stories that we have yet to
integrate yeah the further the closer we
get to it the more it expands yeah that
is asymptotic that's that particular
recognition of who we could be is yes in
it's infinitely deep and the further we
go the more we integrate and the more we
integrate with the more we recognize
this order there is no dopamine we get
like yes more the more especially when
it's like especially when it's I am it
this is one of the things is I'm I'm
still thinking about is like women
involves like consciously moving towards
suffering right but the right kind of
suffering right when I do the hard thing
in this case it is my dad talks about
this you know he's the sober drug addict
an alcoholic great like he says there's
always two kinds of buckets ready right
there's okay fuck it I'll just do one
more line and then there's okay fuck it
I'll do the laundry okay like that
there's this thing when I when I
consciously do the harder thing in this
and this is a whole other thing getting
into this those notion of sacrifice like
when I when I consciously sacrifice
something for the future that it does
root for me or can often reward me when
I do you know like as you talk about
like ever since you use that I've been
calling it ever since you told me this
left you know make a list to do lifts
and just think about like each time you
check it out to a little dopamine hit
great that there is this way in which
like
that our biology is is in some kind of
recognition of something transcendent in
the future it's like aware of time in
some way in that like it knows that okay
if you do the hard thing to go forward
we're gonna reward you so that you do
the hard thing again like there's this
way in which it there's a I postulate I
don't know but like it seems like
something is let let's say let's say
that that's the analogous to a muscle
yeah right that you choose to do and
I'll say the more demanding thing the
more the more demanding of your
wholesomeness your full attention your
love right this this approaching the
thing that's going on as if you're
trying to understand it not like
categorize it but like go on the ride of
it right in a way that you find it
beautiful and you find it to be an
expression of divinity right yeah the
the more you do that's that is the most
demanding thing that you can do that's
the hardest thing to do and when you do
that let's say you look at your room and
your clothes are dirty and you know that
if you do your laundry it sets up all of
these other things and so you can play
video games or you can do your laundry
and you choose to do your laundry
because that's going to create a more
beautiful world right the more demanding
thing what does it demand focus it
demands that you choose how they're
going to use your mind yeah fundamental
experience when we choose to do that the
thing that we choose to do we might fail
at we will try to do the laundry but we
put in a pink sock with our white
clothes and we destroy all of our
clothes but even if we fail the fact
that we chose to do that builds the
muscle of choosing to do the mower
demanding beautiful thing that choosing
to do the more beautiful thing is the
real game oh yes and that must even be
building that muscle is the game cuz
there's gonna be an infinite number of
experiences and and at every moment the
question is how much are we focusing on
creating beautiful optimal experience
yes yes and that's the muscle that is
that'll game for my expect that right
that's developed and that's would you
even say that that our biology knows in
some sense what that is yes this is the
I differ again I differentiate shame
from guilt shame is the question am I
good enough if I'm not good enough I
feel shame right right if I am good
enough I feel we could say self-esteem
yeah right this sense of okay I'm good
enough that temporary experience like
I'm better than them
therefore I'm good enough the guys were
there and for them for that moment I get
the hit but then that is so tenuous
because right or I did the thing I did
the laundry I'm a good person like and
the question is am I good enough
it's about myself it's about my person
that's the shame side that's the
personal side that's the trial side and
then there's the game side the practical
side right right the the guilt side yeah
which is that when I move towards the
more beautiful when I move towards
building the muscle using my
consciousness to go towards what is
deeper and more beautiful and I feel
pride yeah my conscience rewards me well
when I choose to play the video game
when I choose to move away from that to
the degree that I move away my
conscience gives me guilt and says
that's not a good choice yeah
built in that our consciousness the
reason why we value it is that that's
built into our neurology we could don't
mean we get cannabinoids we get like all
of our systems reward us when we do the
more beautiful thing
and it might be very natural and it
might be painful and it might be facing
right I my my book I call it the key is
in the darkness it's facing the darkness
totally courage yes courage
yeah and that well but it's but it's not
just courage in the sense of fool
hardness its courage by going towards
the more deep the more beautiful a
particular kind of courage yes it's
correct its particular kind right right
that's the game like all the stuff is
just stuff there's there's an infinite
number of things we can do and no matter
where we are we'll always find things to
do and the faster we go the more we
realize the limitations of our vehicle
it seems like it seems to me about it
seems to be about like the shame game
seems to be like kind of a hypercar TV
ism right it's like this thing about
like I'm a thing that can or cannot have
value and then I can accumulate it and I
have my i thing that I follow along the
other one seems anyways to be more about
the world it seems to be more about this
self as a as a world disclosure of
something beautiful of something great
and I think this thing about conscience
this thing about conscience about
courage about the good is what I want to
pick up next time yes
yeah it's greater than seeing you I love
going on your ride I love going on your
ride oh all right much love you agree
you send this over yeah yeah baptism
yeah
give my love Brienne I will